Stanford University.
Okay.
Question The question arose about uh
the paradox of
um
if
two particles, both fermions,
make up a boson,
can we have a boson, two bosons,
which are, let's say, in the same state,
in the same state. Um perhaps a more
general question. The wave function of
bosons, the wave function of bosons, is
supposed to be symmetric under
interchange of the two bosons. That
means, for example, if you had
two bosons and the wave function
describing them was a function of, let's
say, X and Y. This doesn't mean the two
coordinates X and Y in the X and Y
direction. X and Y are simply now
standing for particle number one and
particle number two.
If they're bosons, then the rule is
that that must equal psi of Y and X.
That's another way of saying you can't
distinguish between the two uh
particles. There's no difference between
saying you have
a um
a two-boson system in the state psi of X
and Y and saying you have two bosons in
the state psi of psi of Y and X. It's
interchange symmetric between them.
Okay.
Uh and in that case, you can certainly
have two particles in the same state.
For example, a special case of this
would be that psi is a product function.
Psi of X and Y is a product of I don't
want to use the label psi again because
I've used psi to label two-particle wave
functions, but let's invent another
thing to describe one-particle wave
functions. Let's just call it phi.
And psi of X and Y could be phi of X
times phi of Y.
This would correspond to a boson
uh with two two bosons with wave
function phi, with the same wave
function, in other words, in the same
quantum state. That's what this would
mean.
A two-particle state.
And each particle is in the state phi.
This, of course, is obviously symmetric.
It is the same as phi of Y and X. Sorry,
phi of Y times phi of X.
Uh wave functions are not operators.
They commute. I mean, wave functions are
just ordinary numbers. They're not
matrices. They're just functions of X,
and they satisfy all of the algebraic
properties of perfectly ordinary
functions.
And so
What did I write? Yeah, I'm I wrote the
right thing.
So, yes, two bosons can be in the same
state and the wave function be
symmetric. What about two fermions? The
rule for two fermions,
if we put them if we have two fermions,
is that the wave function has to change
sign. Now, that's a very odd thing, but
nevertheless,
uh
that is the mathematical rule, the
abstract mathematical rule, for
fermions. When you interchange them, the
sign of the wave function changes. Now,
okay, so that's uh that's the difference
between them.
Then, can you have two fermions in the
same state? No, because phi of X and Y
is not equal to minus phi of Y and uh
You see what I mean. Phi of X times phi
of Y is not equal
to
phi of Y and phi of X with a minus sign.
All right, now. Supposing I have a wave
function
of for two particles,
can I make and it's not symmetric and
it's not antisymmetric?
Can I make something out of it which is
symmetric or something which is
antisymmetric?
So, let me show you how you do that.
Supposing I had some wave function which
is neither symmetric nor antisymmetric.
Let's just call it phi of X and Y.
When you interchange X and Y, it neither
changes sign nor does it stay the same.
So, it's neither symmetric nor
antisymmetric.
All right, if you want to make something
symmetric, which is an appropriate wave
function for two bosons, you just add
psi of Y and X.
Now, this is obviously symmetric.
If you interchange X and Y,
this one becomes this one, this one
becomes this one,
and nothing happens to that uh Now, this
is a symmetric wave function. This is a
possible wave function for bosons for
any psi of X and Y.
And if we're talking about fermions, we
can do the same thing,
except that we put a minus sign there.
Now, what happens if we interchange X
and Y?
This one goes to this one, this one goes
to this one, but the whole thing will
change sign. Right?
The whole thing will change sign if we
interchange X and Y.
Okay. So, this is a wave function for
fermions.
Symmetrized This is called symmetrizing
and antisymmetrizing
a wave function for two particles. Okay,
now let's suppose we have four particles
all together.
Four fermions. Okay. Four fermions. What
are the rules for four fermions? And for
simplicity, let's suppose there are two
different kinds of fermions. Let's say
there is electrons and protons and that
we're talking about hydrogen atoms.
Now, the rule Okay, so let's see. What
is the rule? We have a four-body wave
function.
Let's now let electrons be called X and
protons be called Y.
So, the wave function is a function of
two X's. Let's call them X1 and X2,
Y1 and Y2.
It's a function of four variables.
What are the rules?
Um
The rules are, first of all, that the
wave function has to change sign if you
interchange X1 and X2.
That's the fact that the electrons are
fermions.
It must also change sign
when you
interchange Y1 and Y2.
Incidentally, let's see. Um
Let's
Let's do this right.
It must also change sign when you
interchange Y1 and Y2.
Uh
Yeah, let's uh let's let
That's the rule. Those are the only
rules.
Sign change when you interchange X1 and
X2. That's because electrons are
fermions.
And a sign change when you interchange
Y1 and Y2 because protons are fermions.
Okay. So, let's see what kind of wave
functions we can build.
Let's start
with
uh a hydrogen atom,
a hydrogen atom,
located at the origin.
All right, a hydrogen atom located at an
at the origin has a wave function which
is a function of its electron and its
proton.
So, one now picks out a particular one
of one of the two hydrogen atoms. One
now stands for one of the two hydrogen
atoms.
And this might be some wave functioning
wave function governing one of the
hydrogen atoms over here.
But supposing I want to shift its
location, how would I shift its
location?
Well, it's easy to shift its location.
You just uh shift uh you just shift the
origin of both X and Y. I guess I don't
really have to do it. Okay.
I don't need to shift its
uh origin. And then we have another
pair, and the other pair
the is describing a hydrogen atom at
some other location.
All right, since it's a hydrogen atom at
a another location,
it has a different wave function.
The wave function may be the same except
that it's been translated, but it is
different.
Phi of
X2
and Y2.
Now, in general, this is neither
symmetric with respect to
uh the X's or antisymmetric with respect
to the X's,
or for that matter, with respect to the
Y's. So, it's not a good wave function
for fermions. Supposing I want to make
it antisymmetric
under interchange of the electrons.
That's very easy. We just subtract off
here
psi of I just interchange X1 and X2,
leaving Y1 and Y2 alone.
All right, so that Let's do that first.
Minus psi of
uh
X2Y1
phi of X1Y2.
It is now uh antisymmetric with respect
to the X's. If I interchange the two
X's, the whole thing changes sign. But
it's not antisymmetric with respect to
the Y's.
Okay. How do I make it antisymmetric
with respect to the Y's? The answer is
take the whole thing that I have here,
interchange the two Y's and put a minus
sign in. All right, so we put in minus
psi of X1 and Y2
phi of X2 Y2.
That's exactly this with Oh, sorry, Y1.
This and this are the same except that
Y2 and Y1 have been interchanged and I
put a minus sign in.
And then I want to anti-symmetrize this
one with respect to the exchange of the
Y's, so that becomes plus, so I have to
change the sign.
Psi of X2 Y2
phi of
X1 Y1.
Okay, so this is now anti-symmetric with
respect to both the X's and the Y's. If
you interchange
in this expression X1 and X2, it'll go
to this one and change sign. If you
interchange X1 and X2 here, this one
and so forth. The whole thing is fully
anti-symmetric. Yeah.
My problem is if you if you take those
two hydrogen atoms and put them closer
and closer, there's nothing preventing
you from doing that because they are
bosons, right?
There may be forces between them.
There may be the the Pauli principle
does create a kind of force between the
atoms. It uh
it will make it very, very im- it'll
make it essentially impossible to put
two atoms right on top of each other,
but you'll simply attribute that to a
force. But will you be able to put two
atoms into the same momentum state?
Momentum states are spread out all over
the place. They are spread out in space,
so when you put the two atoms into the
same momentum state, uh you're not
ramming them in on top of each other and
it doesn't cost a lot of energy.
So, uh yeah, the question of whether you
can stick two things on top of each
other is a different question than
whether they're fermions and bosons.
It can even happen um
that uh you know, billiard balls can be
bosons. You can't stick them on top of
each other. They have hard cores.
Nevertheless, they can be bosons. You
can put them uh
uh you can't put them at the same point.
It just costs too much energy, but you
can't put them into the same momentum.
But if if
if two your
wave functions are eigen-
eigen-value um eigen-functions of
momentum, then couldn't you have the two
hydrogen atoms in the same same
eigenstate of momentum and then you
would have
two uh fermions uh
in the same state, wouldn't you?
No.
No. No. No. No. No. Just take any any
wave function like this.
All right? Is this It's anti-symmetric
with exchanges to X. It's anti-symmetric
with respect to exchanges of Y. What
about if I interchange one and two?
One and two is interchanging the two
atoms.
All right?
What happens then?
It's symmetric.
Yeah. So, it's symmetric with respect to
interchange of the two atoms. And why?
Because when you interchange the X's,
you get a minus sign. When you
interchange the Y's, you get a minus
sign. Minus times minus is plus.
So, let's say um
yeah, if I interchange one and two,
X1 Y1 will become X2 Y2 with the same
sign.
X2 Y2 will become X1 Y1 again with the
same sign. So, this one
will
these two will transform into each other
by simultaneous changes of everything
with a one or everything with a two and
that's exchanging the two atoms.
Likewise, let's see we have psi of X2
Y1, but here we have psi of X1 Y2. Both
of them have minus signs.
So, these will go into each other.
So, the whole thing is symmetric with
respect to the interchange of atom one
and atom two.
Um
That doesn't mean that it doesn't This
is quite This whole story here is
independent of the question of energies.
It may be impossible for other reasons
to put two things on top of each other
in space. The reasons being that it may
be very strong repulsive forces.
But a a good example um
Yeah. Physically?
Physically?
We just wrote down a wave an appropriate
wave function for two atoms, for two
bosonic atoms.
It No, this these may or may not be in
momentum space. They may be anything.
They may be anything. Well, I mean um
what what is it are we saying that if we
have two bosonic atoms, that that's
what their state will be? Yes. Okay.
Yes. If we have a bosonic If we have an
atom
with a wave function psi of X1 and and
Y1
and another atom,
if we didn't know anything about this
atom over here, we might write down a
wave function for the electron and
proton in the other atom. And now we
want to write down a wave function which
is appropriate for the two atom system.
All right? The wave function for the two
atom system has to be anti-symmetric
when you interchange any X's,
anti-symmetric when you change any Y.
And so I just basically use this rule
except I use it twice. Once to exchange
the X's, and that gives me the top, and
then take the whole thing and
interchange the Y's and change the sign.
The result is quite clearly, if you look
at it carefully, interchange symmetric
under the exchange of the two atoms, one
and two, atom one and atom two.
Uh so,
that's And and that at the end of the
day, at the end of the day, that is the
rule that a bosonic atom and another
bosonic atom, when you interchange them,
the wave function has to have the same
sign.
Okay, now what kind of states can you
put uh two
uh
yeah, momentum states you can put two
atoms into uh in the same wave function
that doesn't cost a great deal of energy
because they're hardly ever
uh on top of each other.
But it is true that if you try to stick
two atoms on top of each other,
uh it's very hard to do because it costs
very, very costly in energy.
Um
Let's see. Uh what would happen?
In fact, what would happen? Okay, let's
see what would happen
if we made both atoms with the same wave
function, not one atom with wave
function phi and one atom with wave
function psi, but two with the same uh
What happens then?
Let's see. Um
Okay, so let's
Okay, so there are two atoms with the
same wave function. We have to subtract.
All right, so this is this.
Psi of X1 Y2
psi
psi.
Is that zero or not?
I don't think so.
It's not zero, is it?
Uh
Sure it is. Is it zero?
Yeah, cuz X1 Y1. Where else do you see
Yeah, yeah, yeah, it's
No, no, no, it's not zero.
No. This one and this one are the same.
Okay? So, it's just twice this. Two
doesn't Two is irrelevant.
You know, we don't care about a factor
of two.
And twice this. This is it. And this is
not zero.
Okay? This is two atoms in the same
state. It's not zero.
Okay? Some magic is going on here. You
can't put two electrons in the same
state.
Meaning to say the electron wave
function has to be anti-symmetric.
The proton wave function has to be
anti-symmetric. Both are true here.
But yet, the two atoms are in the same
state. So, ponder that a little bit.
Write down that wave function and look
at it and uh
and uh
Uh of course, the point is, among other
things, that in the atom, the electron
is not in a in a in a well-defined
position. It has a probability of being
many places in the atom. Uh you put two
atoms in the same place,
it's quite true, the two electrons can't
be in the same place. That's true. Two
electrons cannot be in the same place.
Um
Let's see. What would happen? All right,
here's our wave function for the two
atoms, perfectly good, anti-symmetric
and so forth. Now, supposing we try to
stick the two electrons into the same
place. That would mean setting X1 equal
to X2.
Then it would be zero.
All right, so although the two atoms are
in the same are in the same state, it's
still true that in that state, if you
try to
find the two electrons in the same
place, let's just see what would that
be. The two electrons in the same place
would be psi of X1 Y1
psi of X1 Y2. I've just set the two X's
equal to each other.
minus
psi of
X1
Y1
psi of X1 Y2.
So, I've forced the two electrons to be
in the same place, and guess what? I
think they cancel. Yes, they do.
Okay?
So, um
So, as I said, ponder a little bit and
the and you'll get familiar with it.
And you'll see how it can possibly be
that two fermions can be a boson.
Um Does that Does that finally mean that
whereas you can exchange two
atoms two hydrogen atoms in different
states,
you can't
Oh, this in this
Before I set it Before I set X1 equal to
X2 here, these two atoms were in the
same state.
The atoms were in the same state, but
the electrons and the protons were never
in the same state.
Okay. Now, atoms are protons, electrons
are protons.
Whereas if if
if they both are electrons and protons,
you can't you can't have the second
case. When you when you did this
operation of anti-symmetrizing,
um
you basically projected out the pieces
of the wave function where the electrons
were at the same point than where the
protons were at the same point.
Yeah. All right.
So, nothing was left of that piece of
the wave function.
It's still zero if you
go back to fee.
If you go back to what? To I think fee.
Fee? For the second where the atoms are
in different states, but you put the
electrons in the same space. Yeah. Yeah.
Just anytime you try to put electrons in
the same place
or in the same momentum,
it's going to be zero. Right.
Okay.
Let's come back to spin a little bit.
Spin is more fun than we've dealt with
so far.
The reason I'm spending time with spin
is because the mathematics of spin is
what you really have to know to know
such things as the mathematics of
isospin and the mathematics of color and
the mathematics of all of the symmetries
of particle physics.
The mathematics is the same. The physics
is as was pointed out here,
uh
the analogies between these different
kinds of conserved quantities formal
mathematical analogies,
but nevertheless, let's study the
mathematics of spin a little more.
A little bit more about the Dirac
equation, just a bit.
And then, I want to introduce the
concept of isotopic spin
or isospin,
which is a concept which I think dates
back to the '30s.
Okay. Um
So,
let's start with half spin.
The half spin
the electron is a half spin particle.
So, I'll call the particle an electron.
I could call it a proton. I could call
it a muon. Any one of the half spin
particles, but let's just call it an
electron. It has two possible states. If
two possible values for the angular
momentum along the Z axis.
Along the Z axis, we've called
L sub Z,
we've called that M.
Uh not quite. Not quite. Not quite.
Not quite.
Um
There's an H bar in there, right?
But from now on, we'll set the H bar
equal to you know what.
Okay. So, the for the electron, this is
not the full angular momentum
incidentally of the electron.
In fact, I'm using a really weird
notation. Usually, L is used for orbital
angular momentum and S is used for spin.
So, let's revert to that. S for spin.
S for spin, but the mathematics of it is
exactly the same as the mathematics of
the L's.
In fact, we could write it down over
here. Let's write it down over here. The
mathematics of
angular momentum, but now I'm calling it
S for spin instead of L.
I don't know what L stands for. It
stands for angular momentum.
All right. So, what was the The
commutation relations we wrote down last
time were LX with LY equals IH bar LZ.
All right. Now, it becomes SX
with SY
is equal to IH bar, but I'll set H bar
equal to 1.
ISZ
and cycle down.
Uh
You know what to do next. SY SZ equals
ISX and so forth. All right. Cyclic
permutations.
All right.
Oh, one other thing.
We have S plus and minus.
Just to remind you, S plus and minus
is just SX
plus minus ISY.
All right.
These operators raise the value of the Z
component or lower it depending on
whether there's a plus sign or minus
sign, and so they're the raising and
lowering operators for spin angular
momentum. All I've done is change
notation from L to S.
So, this is intrinsic spin? Intrinsic
spin.
It doesn't It could be any spin. I mean,
it could be a spin which is due to due
to
you know, the the rotating basketball,
but uh
but let's say intrinsic spin.
Intrinsic spin. Yeah. Okay.
Let's focus on half spin. Half spin
is the case where
SZ or M can take on the value minus a
half and plus a half, and that's all.
That's a two-state system.
Incidentally, I'm also I'm also
forgetting completely everything else
about the electron.
We're forgetting, for example, about
where the electron is, what its momentum
is, and all that sort of stuff. Just
forget it for the moment, and you're
just concentrating on the spin.
All right. So,
uh
Concentrating on the spin, the quantum
mechanics is the quantum mechanics of a
system with two orthogonal states and
only two orthogonal states.
It doesn't matter where it came from. In
quantum mechanics, the space of states
is just the space of states of a
two-component or a two-state system, and
you can always write it
as a column vector. Let's call it alpha
and beta,
where alpha
is the amplitude that the spin along the
Z axis is up, and beta is the amplitude
that it's down.
So, you can always write the state of
the system, the ket vector,
let's call it psi, which is alpha up
plus beta down.
Along the Z axis, you can just
symbolically represent it by
constructing a little column vector and
putting an alpha there and a beta there.
Alpha star alpha is the probability that
the electron is up. Beta star beta is
the probability that it's down, and
that's it.
In the same notation, operators become
matrices.
Okay. So, operators become matrices.
Let's see what we can learn about the
matrices.
Uh
These components of the spin have to be
two by two matrices.
Why two by two? Because the space of
states is two-dimensional.
So, they have to be two by two matrices,
and they have to satisfy this algebra.
That's it.
If you can find two by two matrices
which satisfy this algebra. Oh, one
other thing. We might want
SZ to be diagonal. Yeah. Did you just
say the dimensions of space are two? No,
no, no. Not the dimensions of space. The
dimen- No, no, no, no.
The dimensions of spin space. Spin
space. Spin space. Yeah. Not the
dimensions of space. No, what I said to
do is to forget about space. Forget for
the moment the position of the electron.
Forget its momentum. We're thinking now
of an electron that somebody has nailed
down to the
to the wall so that it can't move
around, and all you can do is measure
its measure its spin.
It has two distinct states if you
measure the Z component of its spin.
That's it. Only two states.
And so, let's label them up and down.
Any quantum state of the spin is a
linear superposition of them with
complex coefficients,
and the probabilities are the
probability for up is alpha star alpha.
The probability for down is beta star
beta.
All right. It's just a change of
notation, a common change of notation to
replace
this clumsy thing here by just writing a
little
uh
column with an alpha and a beta, and
remembering that the lower component
stands for down, the upper component
stands for up.
In the same way, operators become two by
two matrices,
and the two two by two matrices just act
on these two component vectors.
What did you say? Did you say you wanted
S and Z to be S
No, I said we could we could I would
choose S Z to be diagonal. S Z.
It doesn't matter. You just You just
search around
and see if you can find matrices 2 by 2
matrices which satisfy this rule.
Uh Is S Z a matrix?
Yes.
It's an operator.
It's the angular momentum. It's an
observable. It is an observable.
It's an operator and it becomes a
matrix. All operators become matrices
that act on vectors to give other
vectors.
Okay?
Same thing we've done over in the past.
All right. So, let's see if we can find
Well, I'm going to I could
Of course we can. Otherwise, we wouldn't
be doing this.
All right.
Three matrices which satisfy these
commutation relations.
X Y Z
All right. So,
2 by 2 matrices. 2 by 2 matrices. All
right. They are not unique.
They are not unique.
Uh
And uh the choice The choice of them
really corresponds to a choice of
orientation of axes.
Right? But, there is a choice of them
which is particularly useful for us.
They're all equivalent incidentally. As
I say, they're related just by rotation
of the spatial axes. Spatial real space
axes.
Uh and it is not important what choice
you use. You get the same answers. But,
I will choose the following
choice.
And you can check that these matrices
satisfy
S X
is equal to 0 1 1 0.
S Y
is equal to minus I I 0 0.
S Z
is equal to 1 0 0 minus 1.
You will never find three matrices which
have these rule which No, sorry. 1/2 of
this.
1/2 of that.
Okay? Check it. Just go through it. I uh
I will not do it on the blackboard. It
takes 2 minutes to do.
Well, maybe three. 3 minutes to do.
And you'll find that these matrices do
satisfy these commutation relations
here. Okay?
They are the Pauli spin matrices.
The Pauli matrices are these things
without the 1/2 in front of them.
Okay? But, the real angular momentum
matrices which satisfy these rules here
are half of them.
Without the half, they're called Pauli
matrices. With the half, they're just
called spin matrices. I think they're
properly called spin matrices with the
half.
Okay?
So, this is um
a
representation. I would say this is a
representation of the angular momentum
matrices. A particular
two component representation of the
angular momentum of the of the half spin
angular momentum matrices.
Okay. Let's now see
if we can
find the states.
That means The states means the column
vectors
which correspond to sigma Z being up and
sigma Z being down.
All right. Or S Z being up and S Z being
down. Those are the two possible
orthogonal states, eigen states of
S Z.
All right. This is very easy. We just
say What are What What does it mean to
say a state
whose S Z is plus or minus? It means an
eigen vector
of S Z with eigen value plus one or
minus one.
We expect incidentally that the
components of spin have value plus and
minus a half. All right? Plus and minus
a half.
But, that means that the S's should have
value plus one and minus one. Of course,
that's true. These These diagonal
elements here are the eigen values of S.
So, let's just be very pedantic.
Being very pedantic, we're looking for
vectors. Let's call them alpha beta
which have the property
minus one
that this is either equal to plus or
minus. Let's say plus first. Alpha beta.
This would be an eigen value in which
sigma Z equals plus one.
What about sigma Z equals minus one?
That would be 1 0 0 minus 1
alpha beta
equals minus
alpha beta.
That's the meaning of an eigen value and
an eigen vector.
If we find solutions of these, the
solutions will correspond to the states
in which the spin is up and the spin is
down. Let's just check. Let's check that
out.
Okay. So,
it's completely obvious. Well, let's
just work it out.
Uh the top entry here
by multi- matrix multiplication is 1
times alpha plus 0 times beta.
So,
uh just multiplying out the matrices,
this is going to be 1 times alpha plus 0
times beta in the top and 0 times alpha
and minus beta in the bottom.
Well, obviously this is not equal to
this unless what?
Unless beta is zero. If beta is zero,
then we've found a solution
to the eigen value or the eigen vector
problem
which corresponds to an eigen value plus
one. And surprise, surprise, it
corresponds to a vector which only has
an entry in the upper place.
The upper place stood for spin up.
What shall I choose alpha to be?
I can choose it to be one.
Why one? Because I want the sums of the
probabilities to be one.
So, alpha star alpha plus beta star beta
should be one. And a convenient choice
is just to choose alpha equal to one.
Now, what if I Let's Let's put back what
I erased. What I erased is that um
this thing times alpha beta
was alpha minus beta.
Supposing I want to get a minus sign,
then what do I do?
Choose alpha equal to zero. If alpha is
equal to zero,
this is true. Oops.
And that corresponds to the vector
0 1.
Again, no big surprise. It corresponds
to the state in which the electron is
definitely down and has no probability
of being up.
Okay. Let's go a little bit farther.
What about We've done this many times in
in in these series of classes, but uh
just spend a minute or two doing it
again.
What about
wave function state vectors, whatever we
want to call them, cat vectors
corresponding
to the possibility that the X component
of spin. We're now going to do a
different experiment. We're going to
measure instead of the Z component of
the of the spin, we're going to measure
the X component of the spin.
Again, the two possibilities are plus a
half and minus a half.
What are the eigen vectors which
correspond to the two possible
measurements for that case? All right.
We're measuring sigma X and not the S X
and not the
All right. In that case, we want to ask
0 1 1 0
alpha beta
equals alpha beta.
That's the eigen vector with eigen value
plus one.
And the eigen vector with eigen value
minus one
will have to satisfy 1 1
if such things exist.
Alpha beta
equal minus alpha beta. These are the
eigen value equations for plus and
minus.
Here I've put in sigma X instead of
sigma Z.
All right. Sigma X.
Okay. So, what is the top equation?
Let's Let's do the top one first.
What is the top equation saying?
Hm?
Alpha equals beta. Right. Let's Let's be
pedantic again.
0 times alpha, 1 times beta.
So,
working out uh the matrix product here
or the matrix times vector,
it gives us beta alpha.
This matrix just interchanges top and
bottom.
1 times alpha Sorry. 0 times alpha, 1
times beta. Same thing in the bottom
row.
And so,
is there a
solution of this equation? Well, yes.
All All says is beta equals alpha. In
fact, the bottom equation says alpha
equals beta, which is the same as beta
equals alpha.
So, we solve the equation by setting
alpha equal to beta.
A convenient choice
They're all equivalent to each other,
but a convenient choice is that
we choose
1 over square root of 2, 1 over square
root of 2.
And why 1 over square root of 2?
So, again, so that the total probability
adds up to 1.
If we have the 1/2 over here, would we
be looking for eigenvalue 1/2? Yes. Yes.
Yes. Yes.
Yes, if we had included the 1/2, we
would be looking for eigenvalue 1/2.
So, to look for eigenvalues of SX, we
just look for the twice the
twice the eigenvalue for sigma. Good
point. Okay.
All right, let's see what the um
let's see what the other possibility is.
The other possibility is 0 1 1 0 alpha
beta
which happens to be beta alpha. That's
by multiplication here.
That should now equal minus alpha beta.
That's the other eigenvalue.
Take this away for a minute.
The thing in the middle here, this just
becomes the eigenvalue equation or the
eigenvector equation for an eigenvector
with eigenvalue minus 1.
All right.
And what does that require? That says
beta equals minus alpha. And also says
alpha equals minus beta. If beta equals
minus alpha, then alpha equals minus
beta.
And so, all we have to do
is put into the entries here
Sorry, not this, but
alpha beta here
is equal to
1 over square root of 2 minus 1 over
square root of 2.
All right, so what does this say?
It says that if we take a linear
superposition
of states
where the electron is up along the Z
axis and down along the Z axis
we superpose those states in the quantum
linear superposition, we make an
electron which is let's use the word
right word which is polarized along the
positive X axis.
If we make the same kind of linear
combination with a minus sign
then we get one which is polarized along
the minus X axis.
All right, so we've now accounted for
electrons which are up along the Z axis,
down along the Z axis.
Up along the X axis, down along the X
axis.
And finally, there's the issue of the Y
uh electrons polarized along the Y axis.
I'm not going to
work it out. We can just it's just minus
I. Sorry.
Minus I I
alpha beta. You have to solve this one.
And this one.
Uh equals minus.
And the two solutions are easy very easy
to do.
The two solutions are alpha beta equals
1 I.
That's for the plus sign. I think that's
for the plus sign. Let's see.
Um
I think that's for the plus sign and the
other one is 1 minus I.
1 minus I.
You have to normalize this thing. Yeah,
sorry. Excuse me. 1 over square root of
2 again.
Notice that there's more information in
these complex coefficients
than just the fact that the probability
of the Z components of spin is a half a
half.
Both
This has probability a half a half. So
did the previous case where the electron
was along the X axis.
The fact that there's an I here
something new, it tells us that the
electron is along the Y axis.
All right, so this way. So, now we've
accounted for electrons which are
polarized along all six directions.
What about a general direction? An
electron which is whose spin is pointing
along a definite along a another axis.
Well
for that you have I'm not going to go
through it now. You take linear
combinations of these We won't do it
now. We'll do it another time. It's it's
not something I intended to do this
evening.
All right, so that's quantum mechanics
of a
that the minus sign goes on the other
eigenvalue. Uh I may have the sign
wrong. Do I?
Well, I'm thinking that the minus I
over square root of 2
it goes with the first one because of
the minus I in the You may be right. I
I think you may be right. I think you're
probably right.
So, let's see. So, this one should be
minus then and this one should be plus.
I think that may be right. I
Um do I have it in my notes?
Well, I don't have it in my notes.
All right, that's spin a half. That's
the whole theory of spin a half.
Uh all wave functions or all state
vectors
corresponding
to all possible directions of spin are
linear combinations of the two states in
which the spin is up along the Z axis or
down along the Z axis.
So, I take it back. Oh, you take it
back? Yeah, B equals IA. Okay.
Then it's plus, huh?
Minus.
I never remember.
Um
What about spin 1? We've done this
before. I mean, we've done this a lot of
times before and so I've
made fast work of it. But now let's do
spin 1. Spin 1 is also interesting.
Again, there are many many choices of
the matrices and they're all equivalent
physically equivalent representing the
angular momentum. But I'm going to show
you one.
All right.
Spin 1
the Z component of angular momentum has
three states. Spin 1 is the is the
integer angular momentum. It corresponds
to bosons.
And it's the case where the
angular momentum can be 0
Z component can be 0, 1, or minus 1.
So, there's three possibilities.
Evidently, the space of states is
three-dimensional now. Not not
two-dimensional.
Three-dimensional.
Again, we want to find spin matrices
which satisfy three by three matrices
which satisfy exactly the same algebra.
The algebra means the set of commutation
relations.
SX with SY
equals ISZ
and so forth. Okay.
Do there exist I've left out the H bar
because I've said H bar equal to 1.
Do there exist three by three matrices
which satisfy this?
They're better because we sort of worked
out we worked out the existence
of a three
state
system by assuming these commutation
relations.
Yes, I will just show you a
representation.
And you can work it out and see if
if you can
prove the commutation relations. They're
three by three matrices.
Let's see. I think it's S Sorry.
SZ. Not Z, but SZ.
Or S
The spin along the Z direction is equal
to I
times 0 1 0
minus 1 0 0 0
0 0.
It sort of looks
sort of familiar, but not familiar.
It's three by three, but it kind of
looks like SY over there, but it's it
doesn't have the factor of two.
All right, it's different.
Uh S Let's see what's next. SY
is equal to I
0 0 1
0 0 0
minus 1 0 0.
Notice that this one has zeros in the
third row and the third column.
This one has zeros in the second row and
the second column.
And SX
has zeros in the first row and the first
column. And it's 0 0 0. Let's see. SX
0 0 1
minus 1 0.
There's a real symmetry between them.
Each one has a 1 and a minus 1.
They're all antisymmetric.
They're all antisymmetric. Each one has
a 1 and a minus 1.
And it has zeros all along the row and
diagonal that match the letter here. If
Z stands for three
then the third row and third column are
zero.
If Y stands for two, the second row and
second column are zero and so forth. So,
they're easy to remember.
The only trouble I ever have is
remembering the signs.
And again, you check those by checking
the commutation relations.
Okay. And they're not they're not
completely unique, but uh
Let's see if we can find
the eigenstates of Sz.
This time Sz is not diagonal. I have not
chosen Sz to be diagonal.
But nevertheless, we can certainly work
out what the what the eigenstates are.
Not they're not too hard to guess.
Um
So, we want to solve Sz
on
Well, we want to take this matrix
and now multiply it not by alpha and
beta, but by alpha, beta, and gamma.
How many What What should the
eigenvalues be?
1, 0, and -1. Those are the three states
of Z component.
Let's try for one first.
I hope I have them written down.
Yeah, good news, I do.
No.
Um yeah.
Yeah, it's just
Incidentally, this this corner of it
over here is very similar to uh
uh the Sy over here.
So, it's going to be similar.
I think it's 1, -i, and 0.
So, here's an eigenvector. I think this
is a true relationship. You can check it
later.
Uh
Here is an eigenvector with eigenvalue
+1.
It corresponds to the state where S sub
Z where or where where m is equal to +1.
I didn't give it to you Sz in the
simplest possible form. I gave it to you
in a very symmetric form where X and Y
and Z look very similar to each other.
But nevertheless, the right way to find
the state which corresponds to m equals
+1 is just to find the eigenvector with
eigenvalue +1.
All right. What about uh the eigenvalue
-1?
That turns out to be this one.
minus
And what about the eigenvalue 0?
Oh, incidentally, you should put a 1
over square root of 2 if you want them
to add up to uh right.
Okay, what about the eigenvalue 0?
Anybody see what the what the
eigenvector with eigenvalue 0 is?
0 0 1.
This one is obvious.
Take the top row, multiply it this, you
get 0 because there's nothing to match
this one.
Likewise here,
this is just plain 0.
Big fat 0.
Okay, what do these things mean? These
mean that the three states m equal to
+1,
m equal to -1, and m equal to 0
correspond to the vectors
1, -i, 0,
1, i, 0,
0, 0, 1.
These you might want to put a square
root of 2 if you like to to make the
probability add up to 1.
All right. So, again, we really do find
and you'll find there were no other
eigenvectors, no other eigenvalues.
That's it. And these are the the
mathematical representations
of the very abstract things we did last
time.
One of the marvelous things is that
these square roots of 2 really do turn
up in experimental predictions and we're
going to do a couple of them, but not
with ordinary spin, but with isotopic
spin.
I'm going to show you how those square
roots of 2 turn up in various
experimental quantities.
Um but not not now.
Can we read the second
uh column? Are those are both 1 over the
square root of 2? No, i over the square
root of 2.
That's i over the square root of 2. And
the first one is 1 and i. And -i over
the square root of 2.
1 over the square root of 2, -i over the
square root of 2, and 0.
1 over root 2, i over root 2, and 0.
This is I think m = 1. This is m = -1.
And this is m = 0.
Now, as I said, there are other
representations. There are other
triplets of matrices which satisfy the
same algebra, but they are in fact
physically completely equivalent.
And I'm not going to go into the reasons
for that now.
These are a good set of matrices to work
with. They're
fairly elegant and
we'll use them. We'll use them
more than once.
Okay. Um
Another question.
Yeah.
Supposing we now return
to the real electron which can move
around in space.
It can move around in space,
so it has a position or a momentum,
and a spin.
Incidentally, spin and position are
things which can simultaneously be
measured. Spin and momentum are things
which can simultaneously be
be measured.
What are the things which can't
simultaneously be measured? Well,
position and momentum,
but also the different components of the
spin.
They don't commute with each other. But
spin and momentum do commute with each
other.
All right. How do we represent the wave
function or the state vector of a
electron given the fact that it also has
a position? It has a position and a
spin.
And the answer is we turn these two
component
They're called spinors.
They're called spinors. This is what a
spinor is. The right-hand side, a
two-component object like this,
which just represents up spin, down
spin, is called a spinor.
All right.
We just turn the spinor components into
functions of position.
All right.
So, let's
let's imagine that now. The electron is
free to move around.
The full state of the electron
is described not just by a simple
function of X, but by two functions of
X. Let's call it psi up and psi down
of X. And if we like, we can just make a
symbolic notation where we put them in a
column.
What's the meaning of this?
The meaning of this is the following,
that
you don't just ask
what's the probability that the electron
is up or the electron is down. You ask a
more refined question. The more refined
question is, if the electron is found at
position X,
what is the probability that it's up?
That may depend on X.
So, the probability that the electron is
up
might depend on where you look.
All right.
Uh another way of saying it is
classically, this corresponds to the
classical statement that the spin of the
electron could vary from place to place.
Quantum mechanically, what varies is the
probability to find it up, the
probability to find it down.
And so, at every point in space,
each point in space,
you have a spinor,
and the spinor tells you at that point
in space, what's the probability the
electron is up? Well, it's psi star psi
up psi up of X.
That's the probability that if you look
at point X and discover an electron
there,
and then measure the Z compo- and then
measure the the the spin, the Z
component of the spin, this is the
probability it will be up.
And psi star
down of X,
psi down of X is the probability that
it's down.
But at each point X, you have all of
this apparatus here in exactly this
form.
And that's the whole story of what an
electron is.
An electron is a particle described by a
wave function which has two components.
The two components being
the amplitude that the electron is up or
down.
Okay.
What about a spin 1 particle?
Exactly the same. A spin 1 Well, not
exactly the same. Almost exactly the
same.
But the spin 1 particle, and I'm not
going to call it psi. Let's just give it
another name, phi. Phi is a more common
name for bosons, and spin 1 particles
are always bosons.
So,
it becomes
phi 1 of X,
phi 2 of X,
phi of X
where at each point of space
at each point of space
this 51, 52, and 53 replace alpha, beta,
and gamma from before.
53 of X, yeah, okay, you you understand.
Um
So, it's just reproducing exactly the
same structure over and over in space.
And um
that's that's what spinners are.
Yeah.
I'm not sure if this is 51 the
probability that it's spin one.
52 No. No. No. Okay, so let's go back.
Let's go back. Good. That's a good
question. All right, let's find out
let's ask, what is the probability
Here's our wave function. What is the
probability that the electron has
uh spin
plus along the Z axis and spin minus
along the Z axis and spin zero. Okay,
let's work it out.
Here's what we have to do.
Remember those eigen vectors, the eigen
vectors of spin.
For the spin one, not for the spin zero.
Where are they?
Hm?
Okay, for m equals 1, that's spin up
along the Z axis, the eigen vector was 1
over square root of 2
minus I
and zero.
This is the eigen vector for m equals 1.
Now, I'll remind you
what the rule is for calculating the
probability
for this condition
given
this wave function.
The rule is take the inner product
of this
with the complex conjugate of this.
We take the inner product of this
with the bra vector corresponding to
this ket vector, which is its complex
conjugate, and then square it. Take it
to the it times its complex conjugate.
So, what we do, here's the rule
standard quantum mechanical rule, we
take the inner product, we'll call this
state here phi
and let's call this m equals 1.
We take that inner product and then
square it.
We'll take its absolute value squared.
It times its complex conjugate.
All right.
How about this bra vector that I've
called m equals 1?
Bra vectors are always complex
conjugates of ket vectors.
Okay? So, that means the bra vector can
be thought of as a row vector.
That's just an uh
convention. 1 over square root of 2 plus
I over the square root of 2 and zero.
Plus I because it's the complex
conjugate in the second place here, I
over square root of 2.
We take the inner product of that
with
51, 52, 53.
What is that?
I over the square root of 2 51
No, 1 over square root of 2 51, right?
51 over square root of 2
plus I
52 over square root of 2
and that's it.
1 over square root of 2 51, 52 over
square root of 2 times I and then we
multiply this by its complex conjugate.
All right. So, what do we get? What's
the complex conjugate What What does
this times its complex conjugate give?
I think it's just 51 squared plus 52
squared over 2.
Right?
This times its complex conjugate
will give 51 squared plus 52 squared
over 2.
So, the probability that the electron is
up along the Z axis
appears to be 51 squared plus 52 squared
over 2.
What about the probability that it's
down along the Z axis?
I think it's the same.
51 squared minus 52 squared? I don't
think so. Is it um
Hm? No, I don't think so. It can't be
negative.
All right, I think it's the same.
For this uh
For this state it's the same.
Uh what about um
what about the probability that the Z
component of spin is zero?
That's 53 squared. In that case
the m equals zero state
is 110.
And the inner product is just 53.
Uh sorry, 001. My mistake. 001.
And the inner product is just 53. So,
the probability that the electron is in
the zero angular momentum state
is um 53 squared.
Okay? So, here are the probabilities.
Looks like it's 51 squared over 2 plus
51 squared plus 52 squared over 2.
Same thing. 51 squared
plus 52 squared
over 2
and 53 squared.
Comma. Comma. Those are the three
probabilities.
They add up to 1. 51 squared plus 52
squared plus 53 squared.
Okay.
Uh sorry, this this should really be
No, no, no, no, no, no.
51 squared means 51 times 51 star.
No, yes, it does. It does.
It does.
I think I
I'll leave this to you for you to work
out in detail. I don't
I'm
I hate doing things on the blackboard
when I don't have them in my notes.
I tend to make mistakes and I probably
have made a mistake.
But you get the principle. The principle
is take the inner product of these
things with Oh, I know what I did. Yeah.
The reason I got these two to be equal
is because I assumed that 51, 52 were
real.
They don't have to be real. If they're
not real, you'll get different answers
for these two. Check it out. Try it out
and see what you get.
Okay. But the principle is always the
same. Take the eigen vector, take its
inner product
uh with the actual wave function and
take its square or its comp it times its
complex conjugate. That's the
probability. And notice, most important
in this case is that it's a function of
position. These phis are functions of
position. Can vary from place to place.
So, that's the basic idea of spin.
It's an exercise to work it out for spin
two or for spin three halves.
And uh
it's significantly more complicated, but
not in principle. Not in principle.
Uh
And it's not hard to find the the
matrices, but a little harder.
All right. Um I very, very quickly want
to come back to the Dirac equation.
Let's How do we
Yeah. For three halves, then what what's
the
Uh three halves should be uh four. Four?
Yeah. Let's see. Three halves
Three halves is the case
plus a half, minus a half
three halves
minus three halves.
So, the four states. Spin Spin two is
five states.
I have a question. Yeah.
Uh now this discussion seems to be
symmetrical with respect to time
since X, Y, and Z, but no T.
Oh, that's true. Yeah. So, is all this
non-relativistic?
Um
Spin is something like mass, best
defined in the rest frame.
It's most easily defined in the rest
frame.
Uh so, in that sense uh
what you do is you study it in the rest
frame and then you find the right way to
Lorentz transform it to some other
frame, but
we won't do that now. But
Uh it it really doesn't change very much
when you go to relativity. And that's
because the definition of spin is pretty
much what you would get if you did all
this in the rest frame of the particle.
Okay.
But yeah, we we can we can simplify the
story, just say it's so far this is
pretty non-relativistic. It won't change
much in relativity.
Uh with one exception
which we won't do now.
Okay, let me come back to the Dirac
equation.
And see what the Dirac equation has to
do with spin.
Again
spin is best defined in the rest frame,
but let's uh
Okay, here's the Dirac equation. It had
matrices, 4 by 4 matrices, and it looked
like this. I d psi by d t. Now, the
psi's were
four component objects.
Psi 1, psi 2, psi 3, psi 4. Where did
that come from?
All right, I'll tell you in a moment
where it came from, but let's write the
equation.
The equation is that this is equal to
minus I
alpha sub m, m runs from 1 to 3, the
three directions of space, x, y, and z,
times the derivative of psi
with respect to x m.
Sum over m. So, this is alpha 1 d psi by
d x plus alpha 2 d psi by d y plus alpha
3 d psi by d z.
Plus beta
times the mass of the particle times
psi.
That was the Dirac equation that we
wrote down a couple of lectures ago.
And let me remind you what the
conditions on the matrices alpha and
beta were in order
What was the What was the condition? The
condition was
that the frequency, let me write this in
a different way.
This is frequency
is equal to momentum alpha dot k. We can
write it this way or just alpha m k m.
This is the same as alpha 1 k1 or alpha
x kx
plus alpha 2 k2
plus alpha 3
k3, which is the same as alpha x kx,
alpha y ky, alpha z kz.
All right, plus
beta m.
This is shorthand. This is shorthand.
Uh do I have a Am I missing an I?
Are those m's different? Yeah, these are
This m is with an index. This is the
mass of the particle. Okay, let's not
use m here.
I
Good. Thank you. Hm?
Yeah. Sorry.
And this means sum over I.
Usual summation convention.
Okay. All right, when an index is
repeated twice, it always means you sum
over it.
And we required that omega squared is
equal to k squared plus m squared.
Remember what we did.
We took omega squared by squaring this
out
and require
that we got k squared plus m squared.
What were the conditions for that? The
conditions were conditions on the
matrices alpha and beta. I'll just
remind you what they were.
They required every alpha
uh
squared
to be two, I believe. Is it two? I think
it's two. Uh no. No, one.
One.
Every alpha squared
I, for each I,
alpha x squared equals alpha y squared
equals alpha z squared.
Is beta different for each of the
psi 1 2 3 4? No. No, beta is one matrix.
Oh, beta is a matrix.
Beta is a matrix. It requires beta
squared
to be equal to one.
These things are just there so that you
get the k squared plus m squared.
Okay? But then, in order that you don't
get cross terms, in order that you don't
get things like k times m when you
square it out or k1 times k2 and so
forth, we require things like alpha x
alpha y
plus alpha y alpha x equals zero.
That would be, for example, the cross
term between kx and ky.
All right, so
same thing for alpha x alpha z.
We can
We can write this in a neater notation.
Anti-commutator of alpha x alpha y
equals zero, anti-commutator of alpha x
alpha z equals zero,
and anti-commutator of alpha z with
alpha y equals zero.
What about anti-commutator of alpha x
with alpha x? Oh,
sorry, and one more.
Any alpha
with beta should be also equal to zero.
What's the anti-commutator of beta with
itself?
Two.
Because it's beta times beta plus beta
times beta.
Okay?
Right. So, we can summarize these
commutation relations just by saying
that
everybody's anti-commutator with himself
is two. Everybody's anti-commutator with
somebody else is zero.
Okay, simple kind of anti-commutator.
All right, it's a theorem. It's not hard
to prove, but I'm not going to prove it,
that the smallest dimension, the
smallest number of components, the
smallest matrix matrices,
which can solve this
uh are 4 by 4.
If you didn't have the betas here,
then
you can find 2 by 2 matrices which
satisfy it. In fact, the sigma matrices,
the Pauli matrices satisfy it.
The Pauli matrices anti-commute uh with
each other. That's something you can
check. And their square is equal to one.
So, if you didn't have the extra beta
matrix here, the Pauli matrices would
solve these equations.
But
in 2 by 2 matrices, there are only three
matrices which anti-commute among
themselves that way.
And if you look for a fourth one, there
just won't be one.
Uh you have to go to larger dimensional
matrices. You try 3 by 3 matrices, there
aren't.
You try 4 by 4 matrices, and you find,
yes, that there are
uh representations of this
anti-commutation algebra here.
I think I wrote down a representation.
I'm going to write down another one
tonight, which is a little different,
but it's basically uh it is again, it's
equivalent.
Um
So, I'll give you
an example of four matrices which
satisfy exactly this algebra.
Now,
4 by 4 matrices, these are 4 by 4
matrices,
but you can write them in block form.
Writing them in block form
means
that you divide this up
into 2 by 2 blocks.
You have 2 by 2 blocks, each one of
which is a 2 by 2 matrix.
All right, this is just a
a
simple way to write them down. And then,
for the alphas, for each alpha,
alpha 1 to alpha 2 alpha 3,
put in this
2 by 2 box over here
a corresponding Pauli matrix,
sigma I.
It's a 2 by 2 matrix, so it fills up
four entries here.
Down here, put the same Pauli matrix
except with a minus sign.
And zeros here.
That's pretty easy.
I know, I told you I'm
I used a different a different
um
representation last time. They are
equivalent.
I think I put last time I put the sigmas
off diagonal, didn't I?
Yeah. It's it they are equivalent.
They're mathematically equivalent, then
there are similarity relations uh
similarity transforms which relate them.
But uh I like this one better. I decided
I like this one better. And what about
beta? Beta
is just
in the same notation, same 2 by 2 block
notation,
it's just
one. Now, what's one? One is the 2 by 2
matrix 1 0 0 1.
All right, it really is one, the unit
matrix, and the unit matrix down here.
And that's it. Those those matrices uh
uh
have the desired property. Incid-
Incidentally, when you multiply 4 by 4
matrices in this form,
you can do it by tricks, where really
you multiply in the blocks 2 by 2
matrices. Uh so, there's an easy way to
do this, and it's no harder
than working with 2 by 2 matrices, but
I'll leave that to your devices to
check.
These are
the Dirac matrices, the alphas and the
betas, or one particular realization of
the alphas and the betas.
Did we
I think last time we had beta with the
bottom with a minus
Minus I here?
Well, this that was last time.
Hm?
What's that? This is different this is a
different uh representation. The last
time I had these off diagonal and I and
I don't remember what I had for this
one. I can't remember. I thought I had
beta diagonal last time.
I thought I had beta diagonal. I can't
remember. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Okay, this is a little bit
different and you get your choice. It it
The physics of it will be exactly the
same. They just correspond to choosing
linear combinations of the uh four uh
entries in the uh in the uh
And there's no real difference. It's as
physically uh interesting as rotating
coordinates. So, what you're doing is
rotating coordinates in this
four-dimensional space, which is not
four-dimensional space time.
These four entries here do not have to
do with the uh with the four they're not
direct
the same as the four dimensions of space
time.
Uh
They're just the smallest representation
of this algebraic structure.
Okay. Um
That's what the Dirac equation is.
Here it is.
Dirac equation.
It can be summarized in a form like this
where this really means just this.
And um here are the matrices.
What I want to do The only thing I want
to point out about it tonight
is that there are two
kinds of two-by-two-ness to this.
One is these blocks
and the other was within within each
block.
This
by
what shall I call it? This doubling of
the two-by-two-ness
corresponds to a doubling of the
two-by-two-ness in physics. The two one
of the two-by-two-nesses
is positive and negative energy.
The other is spin.
All right? So, there are particles of
positive energy with all possible spins.
There are positive particles with
negative energy with all possible spins.
All right, we can see this.
And that's why there are 4x4 matrices,
if you like. Roughly speaking, there's
an entry for positive energy with
positive spin, positive energy with
negative spin, negative energy with
positive spin, negative energy with
negative spin.
Uh those are the four possibilities.
That's why when I say positive spin and
negative spin, I mean spin along the Z
axis, half spin along the Z axis.
That's why there are four components to
the Dirac equation. Positive and
negative energy exactly as in the
one-dimensional example that we
described.
And spin.
Up spin and down spin, if you like.
That's why there are four entries in the
Dirac spinner in the Dirac uh equation.
And
perhaps the easiest way to see what's
going on
is to look at a Dirac particle with zero
momentum.
Just take a particle with zero momentum.
That means K is equal to zero.
In that case, we can just throw away the
alphas altogether
and we get a very simple
equation.
When the momentum is zero,
that means that psi
is constant in space is what it means.
It has no derivatives with respect to
space.
K is absolutely zero.
In that case, the whole Dirac equation
just becomes
uh
I
d psi by dt
is equal to I M
beta d psi by uh psi. That's it.
That's the Dirac equation
for a particle at rest.
Particle with momentum equals zero means
a particle at rest.
If it's at rest, the wave function has
no space dependence.
It's just completely constant with
respect to space.
And this is the whole thing.
And it tells you what the possible
frequencies are.
We can write it a different way. We can
write it
Uh maybe.
Yeah.
No I here.
All right. No I there.
Let's see what it says. Um
Okay, so
Here's Here's the way we'll think about
it. We'll take these psi's. Psi one
There are four entries, 1 2 3 4.
And we'll divide it the same kind of
division into blocks.
And in each half of it, the upper half
and the lower half,
I'll put a two dim a thing with two
entries. We'll call it psi plus
and psi minus.
The psi plus and minus mean positive and
negative and uh no, it doesn't. They
just They don't mean anything right now.
Just plus and minus. Nothing special.
But each psi plus What is psi plus?
This is equal psi plus is psi upside
down.
And the bottom one here I think is uh
That's the whole uh
the whole upshot of the Dirac equation
for particles at rest.
It's even simpler than that.
You can
the next step.
Anybody got a good idea what to do with
this simplify it?
Uh that's one thing you could do.
Add them and subtract them. Add them and
subtract them. Okay? So, what happens if
you add them?
I
d by dt
of
psi plus plus psi minus
equals M
psi plus plus psi minus.
All right?
That's adding them.
And subtracting them, I d by dt
of psi plus minus psi minus
equals minus M
psi plus minus psi minus.
The upshot here is that this really
breaks up into uncoupled equations for
two things.
One thing is psi plus plus psi minus
does not get mixed up with psi plus
minus psi minus.
And psi plus minus psi minus doesn't get
mixed up with psi plus plus psi minus.
They They satisfy equations which are
completely independent of each other.
How about the frequencies of this one?
What can you say about the frequency of
this one? I d by dt is just omega,
right?
If
the wave function has a definite
frequency, then I d by d t just gives
you its frequency.
So, this object here has a frequency.
This one has a frequency omega,
which is just equal to m.
This one has a frequency omega
equal to minus m
because of the minus sign here.
What does it say about the energies of
these two solutions?
One of them is a positive energy
solution,
and one of them is a negative energy
solution.
Right?
So, just exactly the same as the
one-dimensional example we gave, there
are positive energy electrons and
negative energy electrons. I don't
expect you to remember all of this, but
uh uh and to be able to deal with all of
this from one sitting with it. It's
worth going back now, finding a little
book on the Dirac equation,
and going through it. But, basically
the 2 by 2 blockingness here
has to do with positive and negative
energy.
Psi plus plus psi minus are positive
energy things. Psi plus minus psi minus
are negative energy things. But, that
still leaves
the 2 by 2-ness of the individual
entries here.
All right, each one of these is a 2 by 2
entry.
So, let's forget psi plus and psi minus.
We've taken care of that by adding them
and subtracting them. But, now let's
look at the enter the entry of just uh
one of them.
It also is a 2 by 2 thing. What is that
2 by 2 thing? It's the spin.
It's the spin which is described by
these Pauli matrices here.
Uh
if we completely forgot about the 2 by
2-ness associated with the upper and
lower pieces here, and just worried
about the 2 by 2-ness within
here,
then
that's the same as the 2 by 2-ness
within
2 by 2 matrices here. That's the spin.
So, the Dirac equation predicts that
electrons that positive energy electrons
come in two different kinds.
The two different kinds have to do with
the upper and lower components uh the up
and down components within a psi plus
here,
and that's the spin.
It also predicts that there's a positive
and energy a positive and negative
energy-ness to it.
That comes from here.
That has to do with the existence of
positrons.
Okay? Holes in the negative energy sea
are positrons.
That's what the 4 by 4 is about.
You can either think about it as
positive and negative energy, spin up
and spin down, or you can think about it
as electrons and positrons, each of
which are half-spin particles.
So, yeah.
Uh can you
can you portray the opposite way around
where the the big
uh the big ones are spin
Yep.
Yep. Uh you're asking whether you can um
Yep. Absolutely, you can.
Yep, you can put the uh the positive and
negative energy-ness into the smaller
matrices and the spin
into the bigger matrices. Yes, you can.
Either way.
Uh they're they're kind of equivalent to
each other, and they just correspond to
reshuffling of the indices.
Can't you go through that one more time
on the positron
uh explanation? Yeah.
You could see from here that there are
both positive frequency and negative
frequency solutions.
The things which have positive frequency
are the sums of these two, and the
things which have negative frequency are
the difference between the two.
Negative frequency means negative
energy. Positive frequency means
positive energy.
So, if there are positive energy
solutions, that means positive energy
electrons. If there are negative energy
solutions, that means negative energy
electrons.
What do you do with a negative energy
electron?
You fill it up. You fill up
the Dirac sea with all states of
negative energy.
You always lower the energy by putting
in a particle of negative energy.
If you want to lower the energy down to
the absolute bottom, you fill every
negative energy state.
Among others, you fill the negative
energy states which have no momentum. I
just worked that out for zero momentum.
Uh but, you fill all the negative energy
states,
and that's the vacuum. You take a
negative energy electron and stick it
into a positive energy state, you've
made an electron and a hole, or an
electron and a positron.
So, in exactly the same way as for the
one-dimensional example,
the positive and negative energy
electrons become electrons and
positrons. The other doubling becomes
the spin.
So, they're half-spin particles which
come in particle-antiparticle pairs,
and that was the prediction of the Dirac
equation.
Uh it's you know, one of these marvelous
examples
of just fiddling with abstract
mathematics,
diddle diddle diddle diddle, and boy,
and then out comes this very very
dramatic, incredible prediction,
positive and negative energy particles
with spin.
And remember that spin had only been
discovered uh as in a sort of empirical
fact from that chart up there a couple
of years before. I mean, just a few
years before Dirac did this. A very
shortly uh
short time before.
And uh so, yeah, it was a very dramatic
event.
Are you saying that negative energy
electrons are positive? No, I'm saying
the absence of a negative energy
electron is a positron.
We went through this before. You fill up
all the negative energy particles, and
you call that the vacuum.
Okay? You can't put more than one
negative energy particle in a state.
So,
the vacuum
takes all the negative energy, e less
than zero, e greater than zero,
and fills them up.
You put an electron into every one of
those states.
That has
the lowest energy because all the
negative energies are filled.
That's the vacuum. That's empty space.
Now, you remove an electron from here,
and put it over here, not necessarily at
the same place up here.
What is that? Well, now there's a
positive energy electron, and the
absence of a negative energy electron.
The absence of a negative energy
electron is a positive energy positron.
Okay? It's exac- it's exactly the same
as in the one-dimensional example that
we did,
where the absence of a negative energy
electron, a hole
in the Dirac sea, becomes a particle of
opposite charge.
And
yeah.
Well, why don't the higher energy
negative electrons that are above that
fall down into the into here? Into
there? They won't fall down to here.
Right, right. But, why don't they fall
and fill that little gap you They do.
That's called positron-electron
annihilation.
And it creates photons. Well, the first
thing it has to do is conserve energy.
Now,
how much energy does an electron and a
positron have? Both the positron and the
electron have positive energy. Why does
the Why does the positron have positive
energy? Because it's the absence of a
negative energy.
Okay? It's the absence of a negative
energy, so it has positive energy.
All it is is a positive charge and a
negative charge. When the positive
charge and the negative charge come
together, you can either describe it as
the annihilation of the positive charge
with a negative charge, but energy has
to be conserved, so photons have to go
off.
The other way to think about it is as an
atom
um
you know, where electron an excited
electron dropping down to a lower state.
What happens then? Photons go off.
Right. Yeah. Uh just a question on the
mathematics. So, here you very clean
clearly cleanly shown how with the zero
momentum state with this particular
representation of beta, you get the
positive and negative representations of
the
uh
psi.
To get the spin representations in a
zero momentum state,
Yeah. would you take the different alpha
beta
I have a hard time seeing how you get
that cleanly because the
there's Well, three alpha matrices.
Say again?
There's three alpha matrices. There's
more than
Well, and there and those three alpha
matrices become the three spin matrices.
But, in a zero momentum state, you don't
see So, to look at spin in a zero
momentum state, how would the
mathematics show that simply? Well, the
zero momentum
zero momentum positive energy state,
let's say.
A zero energy positive
That would correspond to a spinner of
the form
let's call it psi plus psi with the same
psi plus here.
Okay?
Um we want to set psi minus equal to
zero because we don't want any negative
energy part of the solution. So, that
means psi plus psi plus.
All right, well, alpha for example,
alpha is not quite alpha is not really
the Are you asking me how you make
the um
the spin operators from the the Dirac
operators?
No, not really. I'm just asking how uh
if there's
a way as simply as you shown the
negative energy state energy state you
show how you discover spin from the
spring. Well, you've discovered you've
discovered
that the positive energy particles come
in a in a pair.
One which you can call up and one which
you can call down. Now you want to see
that that pair really has angular
momentum.
Yeah, that it really has the same now
you can see that these Pauli matrices do
come into it.
Okay. But to see that it really
corresponds to angular momentum you have
two ways of going about it.
One is through the connection between
angular momentum and rotation symmetry.
And the other is through the fact that
angular momentum is conserved.
Okay. So what you would want to show,
let's use the conservation definition.
What you would want to show is that in
any kind of collision
where an electron comes in
and scatters off something else
that if you assign
the electron an angular momentum
whose description is in terms of this
two-foldness within here, that that
angular momentum together with all the
other angular momenta in the problem
would be conserved. All right. This is a
little too much for us to do tonight
anymore. Um
what we can do more easily
is show the connection with rotation
symmetry. But I don't want to do it's
I've I'm I'm uh
I think we've all reached a certain
limit by now. If there happens to be
another electron around, it can
annihilate with the positron even if it
doesn't have the same energy. Yes.
Yes. And then you just get a different
number of photons. Or photons coming out
with what I'll tell you what happens. Um
okay, supposing you have two electrons
with the same energy.
Two electrons coming in
in the center of mass frame looks like.
Well, I'm assuming that you had the
particle pair and then another half
electron happens to be around.
Oh, it doesn't matter which electrons
annihilate. I mean, the electrons don't
remember which one uh
One may have a certain energy and the
other may have a different energy. Yeah,
but when you kick this electron out of
here you can kick it up to any energy.
It doesn't necessarily have the same
energy as the positron.
Yeah. When you hit that electron
you don't necessarily kick it up to the
same energy uh
you just hit it. You hit it and it goes
somewhere as uh to some other energy.
So the and then there's no memory of
which let's suppose there was another
electron around.
Uh
Dirac sea is filled
and now
a positron not a posi- yes, a positron
is formed and another electron.
Then
this electron can fall into the hole or
this electron can fall into the hole. In
either case you get photons out.
I'm still unclear. So if you have let's
say that that hole uh the positron was
the eighth level or whatever, negative
eight, right? Why wouldn't like negative
seven and negative six drop into that?
And why would it have to be a electron?
Oh, that No, that can happen.
Perfectly good thing to happen. Uh but
photons All right, so let's see. We
start Let's see what that says.
We start with negative seven over here,
a hole.
That means a positron
one positron, one e plus
a positive
um
charged electron.
Notation for a positron is e plus.
Notation for an electron is e minus.
All right, so we have one e plus
with an energy equal to let's say minus
uh with an energy equal to seven units,
right?
We took
the electron with minus seven units
and then removed it
which means we have plus seven units of
positron.
And the electron went some place. Now
let's not even worry about where the
electron went. The electron
this became an electron up here some
place. Now you ask why can't one of
these fall down to here?
Okay. What would that mean?
You would start with a positron
and you would end with a positron. But
you would end with a positron of a
different energy.
This hole was a positron. Now an
electron from here comes and falls into
this hole. This is a negative energy
electron falls into this hole.
That's what you're asking.
Okay. So you started with a positron.
Here it was or the the hole and you
ended with a positron.
It's just a positron of a different
energy.
Correct. So a positron has changed its
energy. When a positron changes its
energy, it can only do so by emitting
photons.
Right.
How do you make an electron change its
energy? By emitting photons, slamming it
into something and having it emit
All right. So a positron from here under
the right conditions can Sorry, a
an electron from here
can fall down to here.
That's just another way of saying the
positron scattered from one state to
another and radiated some photons.
Okay, so wouldn't they just always, you
know, because there's always higher
energy electrons, wouldn't they all fall
down and the only thing you'd be left
with
The reason the reason it doesn't happen
So you're saying why is the positron
stable? Why doesn't that No, the answer
is because you have to conserve both
energy and momentum.
And uh
the conservation of energy and momentum
doesn't allow it to happen.
Okay, so we can work that out but again
All right, so why don't you ask me that
at the beginning of next week?
And I'll show you why
why the Look, you could ask you could
have asked exactly the same thing about
the original electron. Why can't an
electron always lower its energy
and radiate photons?
Why can't an energy electron just drop
down in energy till it's the lowest
energy electron?
And the answer is because it can't
simultaneously conserve energy and
momentum and emit photons. Just uh just
doesn't happen.
Uh
So
Um so I will get in touch with you and
give you the exact schedule. We will
definitely meet 10 times this quarter.
Next quarter I have less uh obligations.
So I won't be disappearing on you next
quarter.
Thank you.
Thank you for your patience.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.